Mescalero Apache Reservation collections, 1849-1963
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Mescalero Apache Reservation collection, 1849-1963
MS 281
Mehren, Lawrence L. (Lawrence Lindsay), 1944-
The papers in this collection include two subgroups: Records of the Mescalero Apache Reservation and Related Source Documents. The records, in the form of microfilms, photoprints, and photocopies, include reports, census rolls, correspondence, photographs, muster rolls, and maps and plans from the National Archives and the Smithsonian Institution. The related source documents, in the form of a photocopied thesis as well as photocopies of primary and secondary source materials, are from the Denver Federal Records Center, the Arizona Historical Society, Eve Ball, Robert Mullin, other libraries, books, and magazines
2.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Mr. Mehren, a historian, submitted his Master of Arts thesis on the Mescalero Apache to the Department of History at the University of Arizona in 1969.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
Series I: Records of the Mescalero Apache Reservation, 1849-1915
Series II: Related Source Documents, 1869-1963
Scope and Content Note
The papers in this collection include two subgroups: Records of the Mescalero Apache Reservation and Related Source Documents. The records, in the form of microfilms, photoprints, and photocopies, include reports, census rolls, correspondence, photographs, muster rolls, and maps and plans from the National Archives and the Smithsonian Institution. The related source documents, in the form of a photocopied thesis as well as photocopies of primary and secondary source materials, are from the Denver Federal Records Center, the Arizona Historical Society, Eve Ball, Robert Mullin, other libraries, books, and magazines.
Godfroy, Frederick C., 1828-1885; United States -- Bureau of Indian Affairs -- Mescalero Agency; Indian agents -- New Mexico -- History; Lincoln County War, 1878; Apache Indians -- Government relations -- 1869-1934; Indians of North America -- Government relations -- 1869-1934; Mescalero Indians -- Government relations -- 1869-1934; Mescalero Indian Reservation (N.M.) -- History -- 19th century; Fort Stanton (N.M.) -- History -- 19th century; New Mexico -- History -- 19th century; Lincoln County (N.M.) -- History -- 19th century; Correspondence; Photographs; Reports
Container List
- Series I: Records of the Mescalero Apache Reservation, 1849-1915
  - Subseries I: Documents, 1875-1880
    Contains information pertaining to the Mescalero Apache Reservation. Included are photoprints concerning Mescalero Apache Agency buildings, the 1877 census roll, a report of sale of unserviceable public property, Mescalero reservation trespassers, reduction of, survey, and improvements of the Mescalero Apache reservation, and records concerning finances accounts. Also contains reports and testimony in the matter of the examination of charges against F.C. Godfroy. Included is a copy of a report of a scout of Captain Fechit. Please be advised that some of the material in this series may also be found in the Microfilm series.
    - Buildings (special case no.l5). 1879-1880 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Census roll. 1877 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mescalero Apache Reservation - reduction, survey, improvements, etc. (special case no. 108). 1865-1877 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Mescalero Apache Reservation trespassers (special case no. 30). 1880-1881 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous records concerning finances accounts material. 1879-1880 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Report and testimony: In the matter of the examination of charges against F.C. Godfroy By E.C. Watkins. 1878 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - Report and testimony: In the matter of the examination of charges against F.C. Godfroy By E.C. Watkins. 1878 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Report of sale of unserviceable public property by F.C. Godfroy. 1877 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Report of scout of Captain Fechit, Fort Stanton, N.M. 1875 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries II: Correspondence, 1849-1904
    Includes selected copies of letters written by agents of the Mescaleros and a copy of a letter by Major Price relative to the capture and release of a party of Indians. Please be advised that some of the material found in this series may also be found in the Microfilm series.
    - Copies of letters written by agents of the Mescaleros. Selections. 1849-1904 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - United States. Dept. of Interior - Copy of a letter by Major Price and letters relating to the capture and release of a party of Indians. No Date (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries III: Photographs, 1883-1885
    Contains six 8" X 10" photographs of Fort Stanton, New Mexico c. 1883-1885, fourteen 8" X 10" and ten 5" X 8" or smaller photographs of Mescalero Apaches and the Mescalero Reservation, and seven 5" X 7" negatives pertaining to the Mescalero Reservation.
    - Fort Stanton, N.M. 1883-1885 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Mescalero Apaches; Mescalero Reservation. 1873-1882 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Negatives. 1873-1874 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries IV: Microfilms, 1867-1907
    Contains 35 mm film copies of primary source material from the National Archives, Washington, D.C. as listed below. Please note that some of the material on the film is duplicated in the Documents and Correspondence series above.
    - Roll 8585: 40 feet. No Date (Box 2)
      Includes:
      Record Group 48, Records of the Office of the Secretary of the Interior and Record Group 75, Records of the B.I.A. Includes selected documents relating to the Mescalero Indian Agency.
      Record Group 48, Records of the Office of the Secretary of the Interior, Appointments Division. Includes selected documents relating to Andrew Jackson Curtis.
      Record Group 48, Records of the Office of the Secretary of the Interior, Appointments Division. Includes selected documents relating to Samuel B. Bushnell, Williamson D. Crothers, Frederick C. Godfroy, and Samuel A. Russell.
      Record Group 75, Records of the B.I.A. Includes miscellaneous records covering finances accounts material for the Mescalero Indian Agency, 1879-1880, special case 15: Mescalero Apache Agency Buildings, special case 30: trespassers on the Mescalero Reservation, and special case 108: reduction of the Mescalero Apache Reservation.
    - Roll 11321: 34 feet - Records of the B.I.A. No Date (Box 2)
      Record Group 75. Includes selected documents relating to the Mescalero Indian Reservation, namely Inspector E.C. Watkins' report on the Mescalero reservation and field notes of surveys of the Mescalero Apache Reservation.
    - Roll 11668: 10 feet. No Date (Box 2)
      Record Group 94, Records of the Adjutant General's Office. Includes selected documents relating to Sutlers.
  - Subseries V: Muster Rolls, 1873
    Contains muster rolls for Companies A, C, D, E, G, and K for August, October, and December 1873 as listed below. These documents are separately foldered at the end of the collection.
    - Muster rolls, Companies A, C, D. 1883 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Muster rolls, Companies E, G, K. 1883 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries VI: Maps, 1858-1915
    Contains photographic copies of 30 maps and plans from the National Archives, Washington, D.C., of the Mescalero Reservation at Fort Stanton, New Mexico. Includes maps and plans of such items as pastures, the Lincoln National Forest, surveys of the existing and proposed reservation, the country near Fort Stanton, and the buildings of Fort Stanton. These documents are separately foldered at the end of the collection.
    - Maps and plans. 1858-1915 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
- Series II: Related Source Documents, 1869-1963
  - Subseries I: Thesis, 1938
    Contains a photocopy of the Master of Arts thesis of Cecil Byron Trammell, Norman, Oklahoma, 1938, entitled "Mescalero Indian Relations in New Mexico, 1865-1885."
    - Thesis: Mescalero Indian Relations in New Mexico, 1865-1885, by Cecil Byron Trammell. 119 pages. 1938 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Subseries II: Primary and Secondary Source Documents, 1869-1963
    Contains approximately 273 photocopied pages of various primary and secondary sources gathered from the Denver Federal Records Center, the National Archives, Eve Ball, other theses, books, and magazines.
    - Primary sources. 1869-1937 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
    - Secondary sources. 1900-1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)